Okay, here we are. So in Sangutara 514,
um at one time the Buddha was staying in
the land of the
magandas at and cavinda. Then venerable
Ananda went up to the Buddha uh bowed
sat down to one side and the Buddha said
to
him, "Ananda, those bikers who are
junior recently gone forth newly come to
this teaching and discipline should be
encouraged, supported and established in
five things. They should be encouraged,
things. They should be encouraged,
supported and established in
restraint by the monastic
code. Venerables, please be virtuous.
Live restrained in the monastic code,
conducing yourselves well and seeking
arms in suitable places. Seeing danger
in the slightest fault, keep the rules
you've undertaken. They should be encouraged,
undertaken. They should be encouraged,
supported, and established in sense
restraint. Number two, venerables please
live with sense those guarded
remembering to be judicious and on guard
with a mind guarded by recollection.
They should be encouraged, supported and
established in limiting the speech.
Venerables speak
little, put a limit on your
speech. They should be encouraged,
supported, established in seclusion.
Venerables, please be forest dwellers,
frequent remote lodgings in the
wilderness and the
forest. They should be encouraged,
supported, and established in right
perspective. In the right view,
venerables, please have right view and
right perspective.
So those bikers who are junior recently
gone forth newly come to this teaching
and discipline should be encouraged
support and established in these five
things. So go back to the beginning. Obviously
So go back to the beginning. Obviously
the reason I picked this suta because
it's um it is kind of one of
the clear sutras that um addresses
people that are put pretty much that
that that says clearly explicitly those
who are recently gone for those who are
new to this those who have not
established themselves um as in in the
virtue as a sapana and so on. This is
what they should be encouraged
in in order to to develop the right
view. So the first the obvious please be
virtuous. So please live restrained by
the precepts. So obviously it talks
about the monks here. So it's um
referring to the monastic code but
generally um eight precepts as in that which
um eight precepts as in that which
emulates the precept of the monks really
the the basis of the holy life how the
so to say is what constitutes virtue. So
is what constitutes that first thing
that a person new to the teaching
ayahujana should be encouraged in. So
live restrained by the precepts um
conduct yourself well um don't have um
unsuitable means of gaining livelihood
and so on. So although it's as I said
addressed to the monks it can obviously
be the principles can be extrapolated
onto anybody who wants to practice
whether they lay person or not it
doesn't matter. So seeing the danger in
the slightest fault in other words take
it on seriously keep the rules you've
undertaken um because that's the beginning of that
um because that's the beginning of that
that right
training towards the right
view. So further they should be
encouraged supported established in
sense restraint. So this is now like on
the level of so okay you're not breaking
the virtue anymore. You have been
established in the precepts you are able
to contain yourself within that. uh but
now on a on a more subtler level in a
way you need to be paying attention to
what you choose to attend and what for.
So like it becomes a bit more specific
in the sense you're guarding the sense
doors. In other words, even before you
would have looked or acted towards
things, you foresee the impact that
would have on sense doors on your
senses. So you guard it by not even
allowing it to come across that. So
basically avoid unsuitable places, avoid
unsuitable sight, sounds, smell, taste,
touches because you know what will come
through the sense
doors. That's why remember to be
judicious and on guard. So to to to
prevent things from arising
unnecessarily uh to be unnecessarily bothered by
uh to be unnecessarily bothered by
hindrances basically and by mind
overwhelmed by lust aversion and so on.
All of that can be avoided if you guard
your sense doors. That's why the mind is
guided by recollection. It's guided by
sati. It's guided by that right context.
So you know the context that you want to
develop. You know what you need to
protect. Then you will immediately know
what's unsuitable for
it. And then don't pretend that you
don't know it. Instead use it to okay no
I won't go
there. Although I might think I could
handle it. The point is I need to
prevent the senses to even get in touch
with these things even if I can handle
it because there will be plenty of
opportunities that you can't prevent and
the senses will be bombarded and then
you can practice your handling of it but
there is no reason to give into that
when it's uh when it's not
necessary. So the third thing there
should be encouraged support established
in limiting the speech. So speak little
put limit on your speech. Obviously,
other suitors address this as well. Uh,
speak truthfully. Don't engage in
pointless chitchat, tailbearing, gossip,
backstabbing, all that stuff. Slander,
you know, like gets proper and
wholesome. Um, so because that's the
pretty much the next layer of of that
that will that will be ripe for
improvement to put it that way. Uh,
fourth thing, they should be encouraged,
supported, and established in seclusion.
So, the actual physical seclusion. So if
your environment does not necessarily
always provide you opportunity for
seclusion, well whenever you can, you
seek it. So frequent remote lodgings in
the wilderness and the forest. Even
monks, see frequent, it doesn't
necessarily mean go and live there
permanently, but whenever you can go
there and spend
time. Uh we'll see why that's important
later when we address the more specific
questions. Um so and then the fifth
thing that should be encouraged
supported and is vendors please have the
right view and the right
perspective. So that's kind of almost
uh well it can be I guess a bit
confusing as in like well so what you
just encourage somebody to have the
right view and they'll have the right
view. Well uh in a way yes if they have
completed and developed and purified all
the previous steps that are clearly
outlined in a certain sequence then you
don't need a lot of knowledge or theory
to understand what the root of suffering
is. So in other words, all the theory
that you know now, all the information
that you have now, all the connections,
parallels, insights that you have now on
account of studying the sutas, listening
the talks, well the reason you're not
sapana is because of all these previous
factors that you have not
developed because very little is enough
when the mind becomes pliable.
So that's the whole point of these
things that uh a junior monk or a new to
the training should be encouraged is to
make this mind pliable so that then when
you start reflecting on the root of
suffering you start thinking about a
craving it will be the craving and the
root of suffering you're thinking of the
mind will be seeing that because the
mind is not obscured uh it's not as wild
and you could direct it hold on I need
to understand this and then the mind
will stay on that as opposed to Now when
you think you're directing it towards
understanding I don't know root of
suffering the mind revolves around the
idea of the root of suffering. It's not
the actual root of suffering because for
that the mind needs to become pliable
and less movable. Let's to put it that
way. So that's why it's like this this
sounds almost like an instruction
because it is an instruction like once
you have tamed your mind sufficiently
when it's pliable
enough then yeah please dwell recollect
ponder what you learned about the right
view about the four noble truths about
uh what causes suffering any any aspect
of the dharma that comes up the mind
will be able to stay with
it won't drift drift off into
abstraction and theory and the external
standpoint to your own experience. It
will be there
applicable. So again that's why none of
these steps are optional or negotiable
because uh sending the mind in the
direction of understanding the dharma if
that mind is not tamed and pliable no
such thing is possible. I mean the same
principle extends all the way to
aranchship as other sutras would say.
Remember when he fully like fully
purifies his mind from the hindrances
establishes on the level of Janna, first
Janna, second Janna, third Janna for
Janna, how the sutas would describe the
whole thing the maximum development and
then he says he would just then direct
his mind if there were previous lives to
remember the mind would remember. If the
divine ear is to be developed the mind
would develop it or he would direct it
to understand the root of all asavas and
abandon them all and the mind would do
it. the mind would abandon it because it
has learned to to listen to you to trust
you and basically above all to to not
resist you. So that's why the the last
you. So that's why the the last
part it does involve active effort in
terms of trying to really understand
what the root of dooka is but it cannot
possibly be done if the actual mind is
not made pliable enough through the
previous steps that have to remain there
maintained protected built upon.
So that's why uh I I I picked this suta
because the the entire principle of this
training it doesn't matter if you're a
monk doesn't matter if you're a
householder it remains the
same the pliability of the mind through
taming restraint mindfulness and by the
way you might have noticed that there is
absolutely no mention of meditation as
in not the concentration practices not
even mention of samadi for that matter
any suta as any of the step any of the
steps because how can you be composing
and unifying your mind whichever
translation you want to use if you're
not even seeing your chitta for what it
is if you haven't even tamed it to
understand it as that phenomenon as that
entity that lives in in in the heart of
your being as I as I often
say so the whole the whole well I mean
we said that many times that the whole
practice today is just upside
But the point is even the right samadi
there is no place for it here because
that can come
only once there is actually right view
right perspective as many other sutras would
perspective as many other sutras would
say and say exactly that the right view
comes first. So in this case the right
view comes first as the beginning of the
actual sort of party the beginning of
the actual knowledge of what the
training is but you could see that right
view depends on these conditions that
have to be developed. So if you wonder
how do I begin practicing? Well, wonder
no more. You begin by virtue, sense
restraint, recollection,
um taking care of your speech, not
letting slip or engage allow and
wholesome unh wholesome intentions to
express themselves through speech
because obviously okay actions you you
let's say you covered then apply the
same thing to the mind. That's the whole
point of the seclusion withdrawal. When
you when your own thoughts get more
amplified, that that whole thing becomes
more palpable, more visible, more um
well, more more more acute, more real,
less abstract, uh less fleeting. Um it's
it's it's harder to ignore it. All of
that comes with seclusion. And so yeah,
you have outline clearly outlined steps
that you could even do as a puja.
So you don't need to to to be trying to
get you know sorti through like yeah
well I know sort of starts practice
starts with sapati but I don't know how
to get there so I'm just doing
everything and nothing. It describes how
you get there. And as I said even when
you think about sodapati now even if you
think in the right
terms the reason why that does not
result in you becoming a sapana is
because the mind is not pliable enough.
So how do you how do you make it pliable
enough? Well, it's pretty clear and
pretty straightforward in a way, but um
it does boil down to actual training and
doing and
repetition. So, it's not given it
doesn't fall from sky and then you just
get the right view and then then you do
the right work and stuff like that. So the
So the
um the few questions that we also
can ask on the base of the suta from the
start like what does it mean to see the
danger in the slightest fault? like
practically speaking in a in your own
life whether you're a monk or or a or a
householder.
Um does it mean you know becoming
neurotic about everything and
nothing like you know everything is
like you know everything is
dangerous or there is some wisdom
involved in this and yes in the
beginning maybe you might be fearing
everything but fundamentally it's like
seeing the danger in the slightest
fault. Well what's the danger? What's
the danger that you're seeing? The
danger of what are you clear? Are you
clear with that? So if you're not, well,
that's certainly a reflection you should
be engaging
in because it's not dangerous just
because the Buddha said so. You need you
need to see the danger in the slightest
fault. So whether it's a big fault or
the small
fault, there should be the same threat
of danger seen in
either. So if you're not clear, well,
you better become clear.
So then um as I said so how can you then
uh mirror this kind of restraint or
precepts moral commitments? Well, we
spoke about it many times. You take on
the precepts by body. You protect them.
When you break them, you confess
them. You don't you don't psychologize,
reason, and explain that I wasn't really
affected. I had to do it. It doesn't
matter. Even if you were not affected,
the point of confessing them is
admitting. See, breaking the precepts depending,
See, breaking the precepts depending,
you know, sometimes precept can be
genuinely like a gray area. It's not
it's not necessarily uh I don't know
constituting an actual obstacle for the
practice. Say you had to eat something
in the afternoon because you went to
some social function. You didn't really
want to but it would have been just too
weird and you didn't want to stand out
and make your Buddhist principles known
or whatever. Don't want to be bothered.
So you ate something you didn't mind.
See that in and of itself would not
necessarily be an obstacle. But
then not admitting that that was against
the precept, not confessing it, that's
an
obstacle. Using your own reasoning to
alleviate the weight of having to
confess, having to restart this, that's
an obstacle. That's why whenever in the
sutas monks or nuns broke the precepts
and then they saw the the the mistake of
their ways and then they would confess
it the Buddha would say oh very good
that you confessed it because confession
of your mistake is a growth in your
training as a noble
disciple. So that's how you start to
mirror this. Not that you're never going
to break the precepts, but like you have
to take on that that weight of uh
responsibility that comes with declaring
that you're not going to break them and
then break them breaking them and then
confessing
them because in that way you are
admitting that yes a certain behavior
occur which shouldn't have. So that's
how the the whole bodily domain gets
perfected. Um and then after that or concurrent to
Um and then after that or concurrent to
that obviously you'll be trying to
develop everything in a way you keep an
eye on your speech and it goes with the
same principle you know like um the
precept against the speech includes all
the unh wholesome forms of speech. So uh
when upon reflection or memory of
something you recognize that oh yeah you
know I've been talking carelessly or
something you you don't justify it. Oh,
but it wasn't against the precepts
because I wasn't, you know, I wasn't
really angry or I wasn't really this.
You recognize if it were, you admit it
and then you confess
it. But also keep in mind that yes, the
confession can be the growth towards the
right practice, but keeping the precept
does not mean purity in and of
itself. Because sometimes people think
taking on the precepts purifies you on
its own. Confessing when you break
regains that purity. It's like no,
taking on the precepts put you in a
position to begin purifying
yourself in and of themselves. They do
nothing. Well, they might give you um
blameless existence here and now, as in
you won't be getting into
trouble. But purification is not defined
by precepts or how many you keep them or
that you never break them. It's defined
by is your mind tamed on account of
taking on the weight of the precepts.
taking on the weight of the
responsibility behind your actions and
intentions and so on. And like many
monks fall into that trap. They think by
taking on the precepts and not breaking
them and everything, they're pure in and
of itself. That's what purity is. That's
why often many monks fall into this trap
of thinking like, "Oh, if I can't keep
the precepts according to my own
abstract standard of this like purity
that I think
constits themselves, it's better for me
to
disrobe." So imagine the irony of it.
It's better for me to renounce the
entire
training than to uh go against my
perceived notion of being pure on
account of simply keeping the precepts
defined by others.
So there are obvious precepts that are
non-negotiable but especially when it
comes to monk's life there are many that
are just gray area and often depend on
intention and often the attention is
also ignored. So then it's like basically
ignored. So then it's like basically
people start getting off on the on that
kind of high
of externally object objectified idea of
purity comes on account of this set of
methods and behaviors and if I stick to
it I'm pure and I'm magically heading
towards nibbana or whatever and if I
don't I'm not pure either way you're not
pure basically you're pure only when
you're an
arand you're slightly less impure when
you're a sautana
So the whole point of that is to enable
you to start actually purifying yourself
in that right manner i.e. on the level
of the mind and your thoughts not on the
level of adhering to rules and duties.
Silata
paramasa. So guarding of the sense doors
in daily life as I said it it involves
foreseeing things before your sense
doors are even open to them.
So it does boil down to mindfulness,
context and recognizing that when you
lose context, you basically lose
guarding of the sense doors. You
forget. So not losing the context,
you're guarding the sense doors even if
you're not act needing to actively
police your eyes, ears, nose and so on.
And also means that see by guarding by
by not losing the context when you're
guarding your sense doors if you are
then exposed against your will to sights
sounds you still guard your doors. Those
things are still not coming in because
you haven't lost the context. You don't
guard the doors by I don't know in a bus
you hear a music and go and pull the rip
the cords of the of the radio so that
speakers destroy the speakers or
something to protect your senses. No,
just don't lose the
context and you are protecting your
senses. So the speech part then as I
said you like simply
refraining from pointless speech is
going to have layers and layers you're
going to have to peel off. You know for
somebody who hasn't been restraining the
speech just refraining from saying stuff
initially is going to feel like a
massive massive step forward. But once
you get used to that, you're going to
recognize, okay, there's a further
development to be done here. And that's
also how you start to notice what kind
of
effect, speaking less, uh speaking less
carelessly, less pointlessly, what kind
of effect that has on the
chitta. In other words, your chitta will
be u not as
obscured and you can become more and
more familiar with his signs and
characteristics. that define that define
it.
So, and same with guarding of the sense
doors when it comes to speech, you can
also foresee. You could see a you could
start talking and it can start on the
basis of a wholesome
intention. But then you notice you're
getting caught up in what's being spoken
back and forth and whatever else and the
intention starts to change and you
foresee that and you stop it. But then
yes, you have to endure that that
builtup pressure on account of let me
just say one more thing and stuff like
that and but that's a training putting
the limit on speech. That's how you do it.
it.
So dwell in seclusion when you can. So
the purpose of seclusion as I said as I
already mentioned when we read suta it's
to amplify amplify whatever is going on
in your chitta. Whatever pressures are
there become more revealed. Whatever
inclinations are coming up, whatever
moods, whatever shifts, all of
that in seclusion becomes highlighted
because in seclusion you don't have um
well the distractions and things to
engage with are not at the arms length.
So even if you say slip in terms of
mentally you start to entertain unh
wholesome thoughts and this or that well
you won't be able to slip too far back
in uh if if you're in seclusion or at
least if you're frequenting and
frequently spending time in that
seclusion. So that's why physical
solitude is necessary to some extent and
even yeah even in other sutas where the
Buddha said what do you say um yeah to
become a sapana without grasping signs
of your mind no such thing is possible
to grasp the signs of your mind uh
without having developed at least some
degree of delighting and seclusion no
such thing is possible so you won't be
seeing your cheetah if you're constantly
dwelling in in a in an environment
that's crowded and dusty as the sutas
would say so obviously for monks
seclusion is a bit easier, but not
necessarily depending on what monastery
you live in. Uh sometimes you actually
have more say in your seclusion when
you're a
layman. But uh you can change the
monasteries, you can change the places,
but as a layman, yeah, whenever you have
the opportunity for seclusion, do not
neglect it. Even if it doesn't feel like
a big
deal, dwelling in it, getting used to it
means basically getting used to the
signs of your own mind. Especially if
it's not just you you jump into
seclusion or have views that seclusion
will magically on its own just make you
understand the dharma. But no, you are
virtuous. You are practicing restraint.
You are guarding the sense doors. You
are limiting your speech. Then even if
you don't see a direct link between
seclusion and stuff, do it whenever you
can and then uh the benefits will will
become apparent.
So the right view then as I already said
um you can be encouraging develop please
develop right view don't neglect those
reflections because the mind is already
pliable enough or at least working in
that direction to become so so with the
pliable with the mind pliable enough as
I said you do not need uh refine uh um
sort of subtle concepts of the the
connections the aggregates, the this,
the that you could just literally start
asking yourself questions even out loud.
What is
suffering? Like what is it? When I say
suffering, what am I referring to here
and now? When I remember suffering, what
is it that I remember? What am I
designating? What phenomenon is there
that stands for this suffering that I'm
talking about or trying to free myself?
And see those questions now paired with
a pliable mind they send the mind in
that [Music]
[Music]
direction. That direction was always
there. Suffering was always there but
you never sat with it so to speak. You
never made your mind sit with
it. Ask yourself well the Buddha said
tanha is the root of suffering. What is
tanha? What is thirst? What is craving?
What is whatever I translated or
nontrated? What am I referring
to in this experience here and now as a
whole? What phenomena is there? Even if
it's vague, give there has to be
something I'm talking about. What is
it? Let me understand
that like you tried that before. It's
going to fall into psychizations,
um, philosophizing, theory, connections in
philosophizing, theory, connections in
space and time.
um oh structure is the aggregates is
this is because of that but you haven't
sat with it because if you sit with it
you don't need to talk much so to speak
you already did the work of
um taming the mind making it pliable
enough then even rightly directed
questions would land where they're
supposed to land and bring you closer to
actually see it for
yourself. So that's what the suta
encourages like please have the right
view develop it so to have
it. So I was uh reminded of something
when you were talking about the keeping
the precepts and then having this idea
that precepts by themselves or keeping
the precepts by themselves will somehow
result in you your becoming pure. And uh
I was uh reminded there's this uh story
uh I came across in one of the books by
Victor Frankl where he talks about uh
it's happening in the first world war
and there's a German general standing in
the trenches and beside this German
general there there is a Jewish doctor
covering and trembling with fear because
you know the opposite side is shooting
constantly and the German general says,
"Ah, look at you." You know, the Jew uh
being spineless and afraid, you know,
cowering and trembling and standing
there um um all supposedly courageous and so
um um all supposedly courageous and so
on and so forth. And the the doctor
says, "Well, you know, you said that I'm
uh I'm uh afraid and and that I'm uh
here cowering and uh uh don't have the
courage that you have, but I assure you
if you felt so much uh fear as I do, I
can guarantee you that you'll be long
gone from here." And the the the main
idea behind this is that it's not so
much about you know uh uh not for
example in this particular context
sensing fear but being able to actually
uh position yourself in such a way that
you don't respond to it. And the same
thing. Yes, precisely. And the same
thing with regards to what you were
saying uh um uh with the precepts. There
are people who for some reason one one
reason or another who would understand
these complex comic connections. They
they don't have issues with with uh
following the the precepts. It just
comes somehow easier to them. And there
are people who struggle a lot. And the
idea is again from what you were saying
it is about the attitude you take and
the understanding that you gain from
what is happening in the overall
process. And this particular story seems
to be a very good exemplification of
precisely that because it's not about
you know maybe by nature you're not
afraid if
somebody's uh uh shooting around you but
if you were afraid if you were trembling
like that person would you still persist
or would you run away? Yeah. Exactly.
Yeah. So in this particular sense, I
think that what you were trying to say
it is it is uh the the attitude that
allows you to develop the overall poise
the overall stance existential and and
and the understanding that you gain from
that that this is the the purity that
comes from from from keeping the
Exactly. So a person
basically that feels affected by keeping
the precepts is closer to the development of
precepts is closer to the development of
purity than the person who doesn't
because they took them on uh on account
of tremendous inspiration, faith, the
authority of Ajan, the tradition,
uh the culture, the the philosophical
reasoning. So basically if precepts are
taken rightly at any given time you
recognize that you cannot keep them if
you don't want to. There is no
external authority or value that
dictates keeping the precepts in their
own terms. You choose to do it because
you chose to do it. And if you take it
that way then they feel a lot
different because you realize I could
just leave. I could just walk out.
I could just turn away from this next
second. And that's frightening. Oh, I
could run. And it's like, but I don't. I
run. And it's like, but I don't. I
choose not to every single time. But
see, it's a lot easier to take on the
precepts and place the weight of keeping
them on the environment. I keep them
because I'll get in trouble if I don't
here in this
monastery. I keep them because
um the vast amount of people say I
should do so.
uh I keep them because I believe it will
help my meditation technique or
whatever. Either way, I don't keep them
because I choose to keep them every
single day whenever I'm reminded of
breaking them. I choose to not break
them. Then that edge is felt a lot
closer. But that's actually the
training. So yes, it does you don't need
to go all the time with that edge, but
you need to not run away when the weight
of the precept is felt on you because
that's what people would do. People feel
it. a bad German soldier felt the fear
and then justified it with his
superiority or whatever ideas
convictions placed them in that position
and that's exactly what would happen to
the monks they would take on the
precepts and you feel it but then you
learn the ways in the environment in the
tradition in this and then you actively
make the effort to not think about you
choosing to keep them every time but to
go along with
them and it feels a lot easier there
there's a lot uh less weight on you than
if you every single
time you recognize that the sole reason
for keeping them is because you keep
choosing to do
so. And that's why I said there's like a
a useful
reflection well actually a useful
reflection u that both uh lay people and
monks can do. So for monks like you
should ask yourself if say being a monk
is made illegal and I have to abandon
this form, I have to leave the
monastery, I have to take the robes off,
would my values remain unchanged or
would I feel
relieved? Would I feel absolved from
keeping the precepts now? And that shows
you exactly where your values are
because nothing should change. If you
want to be free from suffering and
practice the dharma, there should be no
internal change whatsoever whether you
wear robes or not and there's even that
sut says that monks if wearing the robes
would make you free from a and all this
I would say yes go and wear robes and
stuff like that for a lay person who who
is not committed to that level but
wishes to be committed or thinks he's
committed um to the level of training obviously
um to the level of training obviously
you know he's not wearing robes he
doesn't follow that same form but he
should ask himself the opposite question
from the opposite direction say I want
to be a monk but I
because I have a wife, I have children,
I have to support them. So, it's it's a
valid reason like they will go to ruin
if I leave.
However, ask yourself that person should
ask themselves if my wife were to come
tomorrow and tell me, I actually found
another man and he's going to look after
your children like they're their his
own. Uh, I'm going to be obviously fine
with him. I prefer him. You are free to
go. Would you be relieved by those news
by that news or would you feel oh wait
hold on let's talk about this and that
shows you where your actual value are
values are regardless of what you tell
yourself no no no I I become a monk the
moment I'm
free imagine the mo there is a moment
you're free are you ready because you
should be and same for monks imagine a
moment you can't continue being a monk
are you
ready then you know precepts are kept on
the right level in line with the dharma
and actually are resulting in training
taming
pliability. So if you have a good reason
to not become a monk fine but that does
not excuse you from mentally developing
the same
framework. If you have a valid reason to
abandon robes, I don't know, war or
something, fine. But but that does not
excuse you from carry on the same
virtue, the same restraint, the same
practice. But more often than not, the
entire thing is associated with what you
wear. That's where the authority comes
from. And that's taken away. People have
no internal means to continue in the
same direction because they never
developed them. Precepts were all always
kept for them by the tradition. by the
culture, by the inspiration, by
everything else but
myself. In a certain sense, they come
with a package. It's not about using
them as means for you to be able to
actually engage with, for example, as
means that would disclose or reveal the
propulsion uh of of greed or repulsion
of hatred or the or the scatteredness of
delusion by preventing you this or that
in very concrete specific situations. So
the the initial steps into the wisdom
but they are literally just forms that
you like yeah they become even if
somebody initially feels that that
weight of that responsibility as I said
if they're not cultivating it it's just
going to become a form yeah yeah so they
contextualize it in a way of this is
just you know part of this embeddedness
and exactly and that's why it's not
incidental either that purity becomes
synonymous with
So in other words, if I if I sustain
this this this
um
form uh divorced from that pressure,
that's what defines purity. Therefore,
I'm pure. Whether I make the effort
towards damat or not, it would be good
if I do, but if I don't, either way, I'm
purified by keeping them to the point of
you even have like like almost like a
monks develop superstitious
superstitiousness on account of it
whereby I make zero effort to tame the
mind or understand the dharma. But I
take these precepts religiously because
that's the protection, the parita, the
protection charms and stuff comes from
being virtuous. It's like yes sure comes
you comes from not doing harm but you're
nowhere when you're safe from samsara or
or doing bad stuff ever again because of
it because you're not uprooting
anything. So you you have to basically
disassociate your idea of purity being
on the level of just this mere form and
recognize that no that just enables me
to actually do something about it and
develop that purity which can only come
if things are uprooted from where they
start which is your chitta your
mind needs to be tamed.
You said the last thing basically the
the um so someone who would initially maybe
um so someone who would initially maybe
be confessing a lot might actually be
long-term mid to long term more pure
than someone who might getting closer to
the actual purity. Yes. Exactly. That's
what I mean. Yeah. Yeah. Doesn't mean
you should go and actively try and break
the precepts or something. Of course. Of
course. Cuz you know you're going to
come close. You're going to make
mistakes. Uh but when you do, you don't
cover that up
either. And certainly don't start
thinking you're pure because you
confessed it.
Because okay, I I I I uttered the words,
therefore purity is regained. No, I
uttered the words, therefore ability to
do something about it is regained.